{
  "reference_number": "12807",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only if they’re not ideologically driven. For example, Vegan politicians who want to see the end of animals in NZ altogether."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is imperitive to consult with a wide range of groups and people such as industry practitioners and not only academics for example. It\nis important for NZ to have its own carbon equations drawn up using our factors and not those from overseas. For example our\n\nanimals are herb and grass meadow fed, not housed in small spaces and fed by croppers who use vast amounts of petrochemicals in\nthe process of harvesting and processing feed. Environmentalists and agronomists, scientist, chemists etc to get sound carbon\n\nequations with all the pluses as well as minuses."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only if the climate change commission is made up of leaders from industry, proper scientists and not just ones with an environmental\nmanagement qualification and not just those who are ideologically driven from limited perspectives."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "This commission runs the risk of being like the EU and the UN (Undemocratic and ideologically driven) if it has absolute power."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Adaptation will happen as the factors present themselves. There could be as many opportunities for agriculture as difficulties in a\nwarming and wetter climate. Not necessarily a negative fro NZ agriculture. Farmers are very flexible in following the dollar. Won’t need\n\na bunch of academics telling us what to do."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Horticulture has a huge carbon footprint. There is a huge amount of petrochemicals used in cropping when planting, harvesting etc.\nWool is a carbon sink. According to the international wool organisation for every 1 kg of wool, .5 carbon is stored. This should be in\n\nthe equation. Tourism is using huge amounts of carbon. Who pays? Immigration is adding to out carbon footprint. Who pays? Milk,\nmeat, wool are exported to other countries as a net carbon loss to NZ. Who pays? Human babies and too many of them. Who pays?\nWhere is the disincentive for individual carbon use? Too easy to expect industry to wear the problem and not take responsibility as a\n\nindividual consumer. User pays? Who pays the carbon cost for petrochemicals and other things and stuff imported from other\ncountries? Science could have a huge part to play in assisting the world. Don’t shut down science. Forestry credits should not be\n\nnationalised but should be able to be offset by the owner. Solar should be encouraged. It seems the government owned power\ncompanies have not incentive to incentivize solar. Why might this be? Loss of income? Hmmmm."
    }
  ]
}
